Guide to the Joan Preiss Papers, 1970-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files B, 1970s-1980s, (5 boxes) (Box 12)
  - Boycott materials (Box 17)
    - Campbell's Soup boycott (Box 17)
      - Campbell's Soup Company, 1983-1992 (Box 17)
      - Hear the Children (Box 17)
      - FLOC campaign, 1985 (Box 17)
      - Endorsements (Box 17)
      - FLOC corporate campaign (Box 17)
      - Campbell's dirty tricks, 1984-1986 (Box 17)
      - About/from the Campbell's Co., 1983-1984 (Box 17)
      - Stock information (2 folders) (Box 17)
      - Label campaign (Box 17)
    - Castle and Cook-Dole boycott, 1981-1983 (Box 17)
    - Center for Rural Studies and Change, 1977 (Box 17)
    - Inglehook boycott, undated (Box 17)
    - Ralston-Purina boycott, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Red Coach lettuce boycott (Box 17)
      - Letters to stores, 1982 (Box 17)
      - Survey, 1980-1985 (Box 17)
      - Lettuce rally, 1981-1982 (Box 17)
      - Bruce Church, 1980-1982 (Box 17)
      - Crunchbird, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
    - Resources: report on NY boycott, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Royal Crown Cola boycott, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Fast by Cesar Chavez, 1988-1989 (Box 19)
  - Housing board, NCCoC, 1977-1990 (Box 19)
  - NFWM (Box 19)
    - Florida, 1978-1984 (Box 19)
    - Staff correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 19)
    - L.A., 1974-1980 (Box 19)
    - Newsletters, 1973-1986 (Box 19)
    - Resources (Box 19)
    - St. Louis, 1980 (Box 19)
  - National Association of Farmworkers Organizations (NAFO), 1978-1982 (Box 19)
  - Ed Norman, 1983 (Box 19)
  - Pesticides, 1979-1986 (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Pesticide board, 1977-1979 (Box 19)
  - Pesticide work hazards, 1973-1976 (Box 19)
  - Pesticide law and proper use, 1977 (Box 19)
  - Mexican-American workshop, 1977 (Box 20)
  - Migrant Council, 1980 (Box 20)
  - Senator Robert Morgan, 1979 (Box 20)
  - Mesa Advisory Council, 1979 (Box 20)
  - NC Democratic Party Platform, 1978-1984 (Box 20)
  - Connecticut Mutual Life, 1977 (Box 20)
  - Child labor, 1979-1981 (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Farm Worker Week, 1976-1985 (Box 20)
  - NFWM Fast Day, 1981-1982 (Box 20)
  - Nestle boycott, 1982-1988 (Box 20)
  - Forum on Migrants, 1978 (Box 20)
  - Gallo boycott (wines), 1975 (Box 20)
  - Phoebe Ham, 1980 (Box 20)
  - Roger Messer, 1977-1982 (Box 20)
  - Delegate calling, NC, 1984 (Box 20)
  - Pesticides materials (Box 20)
    - Pesticide board (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Pesticide course (Box 20)
    - Pesticide clippings (Box 20)
    - NC pesticide law report, 1977 (Box 20)
    - Joshua Margolis-pesticides, 1979 (Box 20)
    - Chloradane/Heptachlor, 1976 (Box 20)
    - DBCP and sterility, 1978 (Box 20)
    - Dioxin and miscarriages, 1976-1979 (Box 20)
    - DDT, 1974 (Box 20)
    - Mercurial pesticides, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Monitor pesticide (Box 20)
    - PCBs, 1978-1979 (Box 20)
    - Integrated Pest Management, 1971-1978 (Box 20)
    - Greenville fire/Coastal Chemical Company, 1979 (Box 20)
    - Predator control, 1976 (Box 20)
  - UFW products and contracts, 1979 (Box 23)
  - UFCW, 1979 (Box 23)
  - UFW conventions, 1981-1992 and 1998 (12 folders) (Box 23)
  - Violence, 1980-1982 (Box 23)
  - Walk-a-thon, 1978 (Box 23)
  - WDBS station, 1976 (Box 23)
  - Where Mules Outrate Men, 1979 (Box 23)
  - White Rock Baptist Church event, 1980 (Box 23)
  - Worker protection standards, 1993-1995 (Box 23)
  - Workers Defense League, 1982 (Box 23)
  - Xerox (drafts of handouts and flyers), 1977-1991 (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - YWCA (Box 23)
  - NC Farmworker Organizing Project (NC FOP), 1991-1993 (Box 24)
  - Volunteers in Service to America (VISTA), 1976-1978 (Box 24)
  - SACSM, 1977-1980 (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - SACSM recommendations to governor, 1979-1987 (Box 24)
  - Migrant and Seasonal Farmworkers Association, 1980-1983 (Box 24)
  - Prime Time show, 1980 (Box 24)
  - NFWM (Box 24)
    - 60th anniversary, 1980 (Box 24)
    - Board and staff meetings, 1979-1985 (5 folders) (Box 24)
    - Accounts, 1981-1984 (Box 24)
  - Structure of Agriculture-Public meeting with Secretary of Agriculture Bob Bergland, 1979 (Box 24)
  - UFW and NFWM mailings, 1983-1984 (Box 24)
  - Child labor, 1972-1978 (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - New York Times articles on child labor, 1979-1982 (Box 24)
  - Ms. letters, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Child labor distribution leaflet, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Child labor in newspapers, 1978 (Box 24)
- Photographs and Audiovisual Materials, (4 boxes) (Box 24)
  - Videotapes (Box 12)
    - Season of Suffering, 1981 (Box 12)
    - CBS news coverage (WRAL) of farmworkers, 2000 August (Box 12)
    - FLOC anniversary rally, 2000 March (Box 12)
    - NFWM, Durham: Letter to a GA mother (Box 12)
    - NC Now Pickle Union Story, 1997 July (Box 12)
    - Letter to a GA Mother (Box 12)
  - Photographs, 2000s (Box 31)
  - Audio tapes correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 31)
  - Audio tapes (12) (Box 31)
    - Preiss at NCSEC (Ethical Culture), 1996 November 24 (Box 31)
    - Cesar Chavez, undated (Box 31)
    - Steve Jones, 1985 (Box 31)
    - News conference, 1990 November 12 (Box 31)
    - LSE, 1986 June 9 (Box 31)
    - George Carr at Duke, New Slavery in an Old South, 1978 April 2 (Box 31)
    - Jim Jett, 1990 (Box 31)
    - Talk, Joan (Box 31)
    - Steve Jones, 1983 September 19 (Box 31)
    - Dolores Huerta, Durham, 1994 (Box 31)
    - Justice is Sweeter by Joan Preiss, 1986 (Box 31)
    - FLOC rally, 1999 March 18 (Box 31)
  - Photographs (Box 32)
    - Baldemar Valasquez visit, 1995 May (Box 32)
    - Dolores Huerta visit, 1994 January 20 (Box 32)
    - Farm Workers-UCC photos, undated (Box 32)
    - FLOC-Mt. Olive pickle boycott photos, 1998 (Box 32)
    - Photographs of TFUFW, other (2 folders) (Box 32)
    - Photo album with pictures of speakers, activities, etc., 1970s-2000s (Box 32)
  - Mt. Olive pickle boycott stories and photographs (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 34)
  - Photographs from the NFWM meeting (Box 34)
  - UFW 14th Constitutional Convention with photos, Fresno, 1998 September (Box 34)
  - Contact sheets and photos, 1994 January (Box 34)
  - Human Rights Week, 1988 (Box 34)
  - Photos from the NFWM Quincy march and rally, 1997 June (Box 34)
  - Photos from Boycott of Mt. Olive Pickles march and rally, 1999 March (Box 34)
  - Rally and fiesta dinner, 2000 March (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Photos, 1974 (Box 34)
- Organization and Boycott Files, (10 boxes) (Box 34)
  Wide range of materials relating to Preiss's involvement in various organizations, consumer campaigns, and boycotts.
  - Mt. Olive pickles boycott (Box 13)
    - Articles and letters, 2002 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence and information, 1999-2003 (Box 13)
    - Endorsers list, 1999-2003 (Box 13)
    - Leafletting event, 2000 October (Box 13)
    - Rally plans, 1999 (Box 13)
    - FLOC rally media coverage (Box 13)
  - FLOC (Box 13)
    - William Bryan ethical culture program, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Consignment records (Box 13)
    - Conference calls (Box 13)
    - Contract information (Box 13)
    - Endorsement lists, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Pickle boycott PR booklet (Box 13)
    - Boycott graphics (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, resolutions, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Mailing lists (Box 13)
    - Meetings and minutes, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence,1991-1999 (Box 13)
    - Demonstration and rally, 2nd anniversary, 2001 (Box 13)
    - 3rd anniversary plans, 2002 (Box 13)
    - Newsletters and newspapers, 2001-2003 (Box 13)
    - Presbyterian agenda (Box 13)
    - Mailing, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Mt. Olive media, 1996-1998 (Box 13)
    - Media coverage of rally, 1998 June (Box 13)
    - Media coverage and opinions (Box 13)
    - NC/Mt. Olive campaign (Box 13)
    - Retreat notes, 2000-2001 (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Mt. Olive materials (Box 13)
    - News conference, 2002 (Box 13)
    - Reception and fundraiser, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Boycott retreat, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Interviews/applications, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Juneteenth, 2001 June 16 (Box 13)
    - Mt. Olive pickle boycott (Box 13)
      - Information, 1999 (Box 13)
      - Coverage at Duke, 1999 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 13)
      - Mailings (pro-Mt. Olive), 2000 (Box 13)
      - Meeting with William Bryan (Mt. Olive president), 1998 January (Box 13)
      - Research and resources (Box 13)
      - TV program, 2000 (Box 13)
      - Resolutions (Box 13)
  - Boycotts (Box 14)
    - Chateau Ste. Michell/Columbia Crest, 1992-1993 (Box 14)
    - Grape boycott, 1986-1988 (3 folders) (Box 14)
      - Grape-free zones campaign, 1990 (Box 14)
      - Wrath of Grapes campaign, 1977 (Box 14)
      - It Won't Wash campaign, 1984 (Box 14)
      - No Grapes video campaign, 1992 (Box 14)
    - Coca Cola-Florida growers, 1992-1993 (Box 14)
    - Dole campaign, 1994 (Box 14)
    - Lettuce campaign (Box 14)
      - Letters to Kroger, 1980 (Box 14)
      - Hi-tech mailings, 1984-1985 (Box 14)
    - Executive order/Environmental justice, 1994 (Box 14)
    - Strawberry boycott (Box 16)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 16)
      - Participants (Box 16)
      - Articles, 1998 (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - Jamila communications, 1998-1999 (2 folders) (Box 16)
      - Correspondence and conversations with others (Box 16)
      - Delegation visits (Box 16)
      - Leaflets (4 folders) (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
      - Recruitment calls and records (Box 16)
      - Survey forms (Box 16)
  - Coalition Against the War, 1972 (Box 21)
  - Farm Worker Week, 1980 (Box 21)
  - Consumer task force, 1981 (Box 21)
  - NC Consumers Council item pricing campaign, 1976-1985 (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - FMC, 2003 (Box 21)
  - Campaigns at Kroger's (Box 21)
    - Kroger DV and records, 2000-2003 (Box 21)
    - Store check-Kroger's, 1980 (Box 21)
    - Endorsements of Mt. Olive boycott, sent to Kroger, 2001 (Box 21)
    - Kroger comment cards regarding the Mt. Olive boycotts, 2001 (Box 21)
  - TFUFW newsletters, 1974-2004 (Box 21)
  - Services for Migrants, NC, reports, 1975-1979 (Box 21)
  - AFL-CIO legislative reports, 1991-1995 (Box 21)
  - FLOC publications (Box 21)
  - Darrow show (Box 22)
  - FLOC NC Campaign, 1995 (Box 22)
  - FLOC march, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Grant information and guidelines (Box 22)
  - UFW strawberry campaign, 1997 (Box 22)
  - Carolina Shareholder Action Coalition, 2004 (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Cesar Chavez celebration, 2003 (Box 27)
  - 4th anniversary of Mt. Olive boycott, 2003 (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - End of Mt. Olive boycott, 2003 (3 folders) (Box 27)
  - Duke and Mt. Olive, 2001-2003 (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Sister Evelyn Mattern, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Farmworker facts, 2003 (Box 27)
  - FLOC committee meetings, 2003 February (Box 27)
  - Witness for Justice, 2004 (Box 27)
  - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride, 2003 October (Box 27)
  - Race Relations Week, UNC, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Kroger research techniques, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Kroger shareholding, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Music, 1986 and undated (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Monie Health files (3 folders) (Box 27)
  - Julie McCall correspondence, 2005 (Box 27)
  - Presidential candidates, 2004 (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Aerial spray/pesticide hearings and regulations, 1976-2004 (4 folders) (Box 27)
  - Pilgrammage and rally, 2003 (Box 27)
  - FMC policy meetings, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Quotations (Box 27)
  - Arturo Rodriguez in Greensboro, 2005 (Box 27)
  - Rolling Thunder tour, 2002-2003 (Box 27)
  - September 11 aftermath (Box 27)
  - TFUFW signs inventory (Box 27)
  - Strategy report, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Mt. Olive boycott street theater script and resources (Box 27)
  - Taco Bell boycott, 2002 (Box 27)
  - Walmart (re: Mt. Olive), 2001-2002 (Box 27)
  - War and Peace, 2004 (Box 27)
  - WUNC radio, 2003 (Box 27)
  - Lori-NFWM, 2003-2004 (Box 27)
  - King Kullen (re: Mt. Olive), 2001 (Box 27)
  - Red Coach lettuce boycott, 1980s (Box 28)
  - Loose publications: NAFO, Migrant Education Program, etc., 1970s-1980s (Box 28)
  - NAFO conferences, 1977-1978 (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Reports and publications (pro-union), 1990s-2000s (Box 33)
  - Kroger scanner protests (Box 33)
  - Workers compensation and Know Your Rights booklets, 1980s-1990s (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous TFUFW materials, 1970s-2000s (Box 33)
  - NFWM materials, 2004-2006 (Box 33)
  - UFW fabric flag for Preiss, signed by Helen Chavez, 2004 (Box 33)
  - Food and Justice newsletters, 1986-1996 (Box 33)
  - Mt. Olive boycott ephemera, including tiaras (Box 33)
  - UFW resolutions, 1977-1983 (Box 33)
  - SACSM, 1985-1986 (Box 33)
  - Gary Chodorow (Box 33)
  - Violation and election investigation reports (Box 33)
  - John Brooks, labor commissioner (Box 33)
  - Lettuce strike, 1979 (Box 33)
  - Remembering Cesar Chavez (Box 33)
  - Programs farmworkers have made (Box 33)
  - NC anti-slavery bill, 1983 (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Artwork of farmworkers, undated (Box 33)
  - TFUFW media clippings, 1972-1979 (3 folders) (Box 34)
  - Media clippings, 1980-1990 (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Principles of Vegetative Control, by Dr. Chisler L. Foy (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Human Rights Week, 1988 (Box 34)
  - TFUFW, 1988-1989 (Box 34)
  - Labor Heritage Foundation's 4th Annual Conference on Creative Organizing, 2001 June (Box 34)
  - Ephemera: bumper stickers and buttons (Box 35)
    Includes pro-union materials, as well as pro-boycott materials from the grape, Mt. Olive, Gallo, Prime, Taco Bell, and Campbell's boycotts.
- Preiss's Personal Materials, (4 boxes) (Box 35)
  Includes some overlap with the general subject files and organizational files, but largely relates to Preiss's personal activities outside of her labor activities. Subjects include the improvement of Durham, political campaigns (both local and national Democratic campaigns), anti-tobacco materials, and human rights materials.
  - Speeches by Preiss, 1975-2004 (19 folders) (Box 25)
  - NC FOP/SAF, 1998-2002 (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Suspension of Campbell's boycott publicity, 1986 (Box 25)
  - Testimony, 1982-1983 (Box 25)
  - T-shirt designs, 1978-1988 (Box 25)
  - TFUFW board meetings, 1984-2003 (5 folders) (Box 25)
  - Teamsters (Box 25)
  - TV, 1970s (Box 25)
  - Progressive Jewish Network, 1982-1988 (Box 26)
  - Tobacco advertising ban, 1986 (2 folders) (Box 26)
  - Durham ACLU, 1980s (3 folders) (Box 26)
  - Durham Visions contest, 1986-1995 (Box 26)
  - Durham Central Labor Union, 1987-1991 (Box 26)
  - Dukakis campaign, 1988 (Box 26)
  - Mark Curtis defense effort, 1989 (Box 26)
  - DAC (2 folders) (Box 26)
  - Coalition for Alternatives to Shearon Harris (CASH) nuclear power plant, 1980-1987 (Box 26)
  - Anti-war information, 1991 (Box 26)
  - AFCSME Union, 1978 (Box 26)
  - South Africa, 1986-1987 (Box 26)
  - MLK, Jr., 1987 (Box 26)
  - Wilbur Hobby defense, 1970s-1992 (Box 26)
  - Politics and candidates, 1978-1984 (Box 26)
  - Recall of Mayor Gulley, 1986 (Box 26)
  - Preiss's agendas and notebooks, 1974-1986 (8 folders) (Box 28)
  - Preiss's notebook, 1992-1997 (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Expense books, 1978-1986 (5 folders) (Box 32)
  - Financial reports and records, 1978-1986 (Box 32)
- Correspondence and Mailings, (6 boxes) (Box 32)
  Includes correspondence to and from Joan Preiss and her various organizations, as well as mailings from a variety of labor groups.
  - Correspondence with UFW, 1978-1996 (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - El Malcriado newspaper (UFW), 1972-1983 (Box 14)
  - UFW mailings (Box 15)
    - About Wilbur Hobby, 1974-1981 (Box 15)
    - El Taller Grafico, 1977-1981 (Box 15)
    - NAFO, 1979-1980 (Box 15)
    - New York, 1981 (Box 15)
    - Chicago, 1982 (Box 15)
    - 1989-1990 (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Thomas Heffner, Boone Support Group, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
    - 1991-1992 (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - President's office, 1993-1994 (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Washington state, 1993-1994 (Box 15)
    - 1995 (Box 15)
    - Texas, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Fundraising (Box 15)
    - FLOC, 1983-1993 (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - TFUFW, 1986-1994 (5 folders) (Box 15)
  - NFWM (Box 15)
    - Migrant Ministry Committee, 1977-1983 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence through 1981 (Box 15)
    - Mailings, 1981-1982 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence/mailings, Mission Dept., 1982 (Box 15)
    - Mailings, 1991-1997 (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - PCUN newsletters and mailings, 1992-1997 (Box 15)
  - UFW correspondence, 1979 (Box 16)
  - Mt. Olive/FLOC march (includes photos), 1998 (Box 16)
  - FLOC correspondence (Box 16)
  - Kroger demonstration and aftermath, 2001 August (Box 16)
  - Duke Campus Ministry, 1999-2004 (5 folders) (Box 16)
  - TFUFW correspondence and board meetings, 2002-2006 (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - TFUFW correspondence, 1974-1990 (12 folders) (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1995 (5 folders) (Box 19)
  - Correspondence/fundraising, 1995-2005 (17 folders) (Box 22)
  - UFW mailings, 1981-2004 (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Letters to the News and Observer, 1989-2000 (Box 22)
- Printed Reports, Books, and Publications, (3 boxes) (Box 22)
  - Health issues (Box 29)
  - Housing (Box 29)
  - Immigration (Box 29)
  - NAFO reports (Box 29)
  - Pesticides (3 folders) (Box 29)
  - Reports, multiple issues (Box 29)
  - Reichert report (Box 29)
  - SACSM position papers (Box 29)
  - Statistical information (Box 29)
  - Structure of Agriculture (Box 29)
  - UFW (Box 29)
  - Newspaper (Box 29)
  - H-2A programs (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Farmworker women (Box 30)
  - Education (Box 30)
  - Food/nutrition (Box 30)
  - Roybal and the GAO report (Box 30)
  - Hazards-pesticides and others (Box 30)
  - Migrants/crew leaders (Box 30)
  - Farmworker data network reports (Box 30)
  - Civil Rights Commission reports (Box 30)
  - Child labor (Box 30)
  - Commission on Agricultural Workers (Box 30)
  - Migrant education (Box 30)
  - Environmental Assessment of Pesticide Regulatory Programs (public response), Volumes 1-5 (Box 30)
  - Boycott histories and publications, 1979-2004 (Box 31)
  - Food and Justice (UFW), 1984-1988 (Box 31)
  - Southern Exposure, 1980 and 1983 (Box 31)
  - Pro-Union booklets and pamphlets, 1970s-1980s (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Curriculum and classroom materials on farmworkers, 1990s (Box 31)
  - Guides, manuals, and publications on migrants, health, and pesticides (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - UFW Resolutions from the 15th Constitutional Convention, 2000 (Box 31)
  - Union music and songbooks (Box 31)
  - Books (Box 31)
    - Migrant Farm Works: A Caste of Despair, by Ronald L. Goldfarb, 1981 (Box 31)
    - Grapes of Conflict, by Sydney D. Smith, 1987 (Box 31)
    - Circle of Poison, by David Weir and Mark Schapiro, 1981 (Box 31)
    - Ecodefense: A Field Guide to Monkeywrenching, ed. by Dave Foreman, 1985 (Box 31)
    - NC OSHA Compliance Special Report: Perdue Farms, Inc., 1991 (Box 31)
- Oversize Materials, (1 box) (Box 31)
  - Oversize posters and posterboards (Box 36)
    Includes boycott posters for the Prime mushrooms, Campbell's, grapes, Mt. Olive, and Gallo wine boycotts, as well as general pro-union materials. Also includes posters addressing Wellspring (Whole Foods) grocery about labor issues and 2 fabric flags (1 FLOC and 1 UFW).